<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief and modest reply to Mr. Penn's tedious, scurrilous and unchristian defence against the Bishop of Cork</title>
            <author>Wettenhall, Edward, 1636-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65534</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1489</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38532</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17544774</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17544774</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106565</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65534)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106565)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1108:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief and modest reply to Mr. Penn's tedious, scurrilous and unchristian defence against the Bishop of Cork</title>
                  <author>Wettenhall, Edward, 1636-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Joseph Ray ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Wettenhall by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Edward Wettenhall was Bishop of Cork and Ross between 1679-1699. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 27.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Penn, William, 1644-1718.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106565:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106565:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEF and MODEST REPLY To Mr. <hi>Penn</hi>'s Tedious, Scurrilous and Unchriſtian DEFENCE AGAINST THE BISHOP OF CORK.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Father, Forgive Them.</hi> Luke XXIII.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>DUBLIN:</hi> Printed by <hi>Joſeph Ray,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Skinner-Row,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Tholſel,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:106565:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106565:2"/>
            <head>A Brief &amp; Modeſt REPLY to Mr. PENN's Tedious &amp; Unchriſtian Defence againſt the Biſhop of CORK.</head>
            <p>THE Biſhop of <hi>Cork</hi> being to <hi>Vindicute</hi> the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Himſelf,</hi> from many foul Imputations and virulent Invectives which Mr. <hi>Penn</hi> in his <hi>defence</hi> of a Paper of his own, ſtyled <hi>Goſpel Truths,</hi> has been pleaſed to beſtow upon both, in the firſt place thanks Mr. <hi>Penn</hi> for having Printed both his <hi>own Paper</hi> and the <hi>Biſhops Teſtimony</hi> againſt it, at length before his Book. For the Biſhop be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves, that all ſober and reaſonable Chriſtians, who ſhall read thoſe two over, and conſider them, will eaſily acquit the Biſhop from the firſt of Mr. <hi>Penn</hi>'s Imputations in his Preface, that he is <hi>a man of a mind different from thoſe who would have Strife amongſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans abated, and who are againſt Quarrels and for the diſcouraging Controverſies in that holy and peaceable thing Religion.</hi> The Biſhop ſays, a <hi>peaceable Teſtimony</hi> againſt <hi>the ſleight of Men,</hi> touching whom it is queſtionable whether they be Chriſtians or not, and againſt <hi>their cunning Craftineſs who lye in wait to deceive,</hi> is no <hi>moving Strife</hi> or <hi>raiſing Quarrels</hi> amongſt <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Penn</hi> adds <hi>he gave his Paper to the Biſhop in a private way at a friendly Viſit, upon his own deſire</hi> This is what the Biſhop called <hi>Writing in ſuch a way, that it is hard to know what is meant.</hi> If Mr. <hi>Penn</hi> mean, that either he gave the Paper to the Biſhop upon the Biſhop's deſire, or made that Viſit upon the Biſhop's deſire, in both ſenſes the ſaying is utterly falſe; for both the Viſit and the Paper were a ſurpriſe and altogether unexpected by the Biſhop. But (to confeſs freely all the truth there can be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106565:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> in this Colour) if it ſhould be ſo, that Mr. <hi>Penn</hi> has amongſt the other ſpiritual gifts, he pretends to, that of <hi>diſcerning Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> and knew that the Bp. was as deſirous to ſee the <note n="*" place="margin">The Bp. was inform'd that Mr. <hi>P.</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal-Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> did while he was lately in <hi>Cork</hi> ſay, He had a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of his own: which was under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvania.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>King of Penſilvania,</hi> as he would be the <hi>Pope,</hi> or the <hi>Great Turk,</hi> or any other <hi>Great Man of Sin,</hi> ſuppoſing them in the Country; in this ſenſe the Bp. acknowledges the ſaying true. He had a little Curioſity, which may paſs for a deſire, to ſee Mr. <hi>Penn.</hi> Then as to the Privacy of the Matter, Mr. <hi>Penn</hi> well knows he brought two Witneſſes with him, the one a good Proteſtant, the other a Quaker: And his giving the Bp. that Paper before them both, gave occaſion to the Bp. to ſuſpect, there was ſome deſign in it. Had the Bp. received it privately indeed, that is without Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of both ſides, Mr. <hi>Penn</hi> perhaps had never heard more of it. And thus as to Mr. <hi>Penn</hi>'s <hi>Preface.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt charge in his Book againſt the Bp. is, that he did not prove <hi>ſuch a Reader as he profeſt himſelf.</hi> Mr. <hi>P.</hi> would have had him ſuch a Reader <hi>that had rather they ſhould be in the right, than in the wrong:</hi> The Bp. never profeſt himſelf ſuch: for either here alſo the Bp. underſtands not what Mr. <hi>P.</hi> means, or elſe Mr. <hi>P.</hi> deſires a ſtrange partial Reader, who ſhould have more inclination and affection to the Quakers, (that is, his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries) opinion, than to his own; Or who would rather be in an Error himſelf, than that his Adverſaries ſhould be in any. Such <hi>unheard of partiality</hi> as this, the Bp. admires Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, and confeſſes himſelf void of: But a <hi>very impartial Reader</hi> he was, which he took to have been Mr. <hi>P—</hi>s meaning: And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice both did he, does, and will own the truth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he finds it. And as to what Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſo often objects that the Bp. has <hi>Writ againſt him without any Provocation,</hi> it is readily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged: The Bp. neither had, nor has any <hi>perſonal private Quarrel</hi> with Mr. <hi>P.</hi> All he impleads him of <hi>is his Doctrine.</hi> The Bp. can return Mr. <hi>Ps.</hi> own words to him (p. 23.) <hi>he has a reſpect for him, and deſires not to be upon theſe terms with him any longer, than he thinks fit to make it neceſſary,</hi> by ſpreading and defending ſuch Principles, which tend to the ſubverting Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, at which no Biſhop ought to connive.</p>
            <p>To omit things leſs material, (p. 24.) he would inſinuate
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106565:3"/> the Bp. guilty of <hi>inſincerity</hi> in ſaying, <hi>It was the firſt time he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard the Quakers own the neceſſity of Chriſt, as a Propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, in order to Remiſſion of Sins, and juſtifying them as Sinners from guilt:</hi> And tells the Bp. where poſſibly he might have read it. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Poſſibly the Bp. may have read more than either then he did, or now does actually remember. He never had ſo much as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Quakers Books, much leſs has he them in his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory; but one he has now before him Intitled, <hi>The Second Part of the ſerious Apology for the Principles and Practices of the People called Quakers:</hi> By <hi>WILLIAM PENN. Printed</hi> 1671. In which (p. 148.) are theſe words. <q>
                  <hi>This</hi> [namely <hi>Juſtification by the Righteouſneſs which Chriſt hath fulfilled in his own Perſon for us,</hi> in the words before] <hi>We deny and boldly affirm it to be the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Devils, and an Arm of the Sea of Corruption, which does now deluge the whole World.</hi>
               </q> This the Bp. does not underſtand to be owning Juſtification by Chriſt. He thefore now was glad to find Mr. <hi>P.</hi> more Orthodox in 1698, than he was in 1671.</p>
            <p>But ſays <hi>W. P. If the Bp. commends their believing in Chriſt as a Propitiation for Sin, he ought not to have cenſured them as ſhort in any Fundamental Article of Chriſtian Religion, for that all the reſt follow from, or are comprehended in this,</hi> (p. 25, 26.) Truly he ought. For 1. He does not find the Quakers to be ſo good at believing or drawing due conſequences, or deducing and diſcovering, all the particulars, which are comprehended in generals. 2. It is not true that all the Fundamentals of Chriſtian Religion, follow from, or are comprehended in this Doctrine, Chriſt is our Propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation. Some of them (particularly mentioned by Mr. <hi>P.)</hi> do not thence follow: as, that there is a Holy Ghoſt, that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces Men of Sin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nay, not that (p. 34.) That Chriſt is Aſcended; for he might have been a Propitiation and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice (as were thoſe under the Law) and yet never have aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended, no nor roſe again. 3. To tell Mr. <hi>P.</hi> thus much as to his Paper once for all: <hi>Implication</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> is not a <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of Faith. Remote conſequences not mentioned, which yet 'tis poſſible may be drawn, muſt not be taken for a Confeſſion of Faith. For he that deduces ſuch conſequences, is the perſon that truly makes them: And in ſuch caſe the Quakers confeſſion of Faith, would not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106565:4"/> be made by themſelves, who only laid down the Principle, but by the perſons who deduced the conſequences; which conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, the Quakers would have liberty, to accept or deny as they pleaſed: For no one is bound to own all the conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which ſome will draw from, or affix to, his words.</p>
            <p>Which laſt particular ſerves for an Anſwer, to much that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, and fully Vindicates the Bp. for ſaying, that their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion touching the being of GOD (or of <hi>the Firſt Article of the Creed)</hi> by reporting it only thus, That <hi>GOD is, and that He is a rewarder of all them that fear Him,</hi> is imperfect. Can any thing be more manifeſt, than that here is not a word of GODs <hi>Creating</hi> the preſent World, or <hi>Supporting it by his Providence,</hi> or concerning himſelf about the <hi>Inanimate part</hi> of it, with a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of other particulars? <q>But ſays Mr. <hi>P.</hi> (p. 27.) <hi>by the Bps. leave, He that belives in GOD, believes all that's neceſſary to the Supreme Being.</hi>
               </q> The Bp. demands, who knows what ſome Men mean by GOD, or will aknowledge neceſſary to the Supreme Being? A Great Man has told us, that with the Gentile World <hi>(i. e.</hi> far the moſt of Mankind) <hi>what ever was above human condition, or the common Peoples underſtanding, was preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called a GOD:</hi> And ſo they made Thouſands of GODs: Again, take GOD for the True Supreme Being, even they who acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him ſuch, do not agree in all thoſe Atributes, which Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity teaches of him; For inſtance, not in ſuch an Omniſcience, which comprehends the knowledge of all future contingents, nor in ſuch infinite goodneſs and Philanthropy, as moved Him to give His only Son by Death, to redeem all Mankind; and in many other like points of Revealed Religon; and in a word, whereas Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſaith that <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6. ſeems expreſt for a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Faith in GOD, The Bp. takes the freedom to inform him, that it was not at all intended for a <hi>full confeſſion of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Faith,</hi> as to <hi>that Article</hi> thereof, touching the Being, Nature, and Works of GOD; but onely of ſuch an <hi>Initial or Natural Faith,</hi> which men had or might have <hi>without Revelation;</hi> for of the Faith of ſuch, <hi>viz. Abel,</hi> and <hi>Enoch,</hi> and thoſe who lived before the Flood, without any Revelation that we read of, he there diſcourſes. Now what an eaſie prevention of all this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106565:4"/> and uncertainty had it been, for Mr. <hi>P.</hi> and his Party to have ſaid, <hi>I believe in GOD the Father Almighty / maſter of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth / </hi> but this had been confeſſing an Article of Faith, in a way beneath their Light.</p>
            <p>Again, the acknowledging <hi>future Rewards and Puniſhments,</hi> (p. 28. 29.) no more infers the <hi>Reſurrection from the Dead,</hi> or <hi>Eternity of Torments to the Damned,</hi> then any of the former points imply, what Mr. <hi>P.</hi> would have comprehended in them. The Heathens who in their way demonſtrate the Immortality of the Soul, believed alſo different Eſtates, and ſo Rewards and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments in that Immortal Life, yet never thought of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Dead; and ſome of them when they heard of it, ſcoffed at it, and called him a <hi>vain Babler,</hi> that Preached it to them. And if Mr. <hi>P.</hi> were a man of ſuch a general Reading, as he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to, he would have known there was one <hi>SYNESIUS</hi> a Chriſtian Philoſopher (to ſay no more) who profeſt, he could not believe the Reſurrection of the Body, though he believed all the other Articles of the Apoſtles Creed. And being that Mr. <hi>P.</hi> is ſo well accquainted with the Doctrines and Books of the Socinians, as he pretends to be, the Bp. muſt return his Phraſe upon him, that <hi>it is Mr.</hi> Ps. <hi>fault and next to impoſſible he he ſhould be Ignorant,</hi> that thoſe who believe future Rewards and Puniſhments, do not all of them believe the future Puniſhments Eternal. The Bp. thinks alſo that there was ſuch a Perſon in the World as <hi>Origen,</hi> and others called the <hi>Merciful Doctors,</hi> who believed future Rewards and Puniſhments, yet did not beliefe what Mr. <hi>P.</hi> would have inferred thence, the Puniſhment of the Damned to be Everlaſting. It had been neceſſary therefore for him and his Brethren <hi>explicitly</hi> to have <hi>declared</hi> their belief of theſe two main Articles, <hi>The Reſurrection, and Eternal Torments,</hi> even amongſt the <hi>Truths chiefly believed by them,</hi> that we might have known the <hi>Quakers</hi> to be neither <hi>Heathens</hi> nor <hi>Socinians</hi> in theſe points; which herein it is plain they may be, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their belief, that GOD is a rewarder of them who ſeek him.</p>
            <p>In the end of p. 29. and all the 30. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> tragically exclaims againſt the Bp. for ſaying, that that Text of the <hi>Three that bear</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:106565:5"/> 
               <hi>Witneſs in Heaven being one,</hi> (1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 7.) is not the ſumm of what the Holy Scripture teacheth, nor a ſufficient confeſſion of faith, of the Holy Trinity. He inſinuates (which is utterly falſe) that the Bp. ſleights that, as but a by paſſage, or of little Credit: For the wiping off Mr. <hi>P—s</hi> Aſperſions, the Bp. ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals to what in his Paper he Writ: And further ſaith, it is <hi>no bold attempt in one of his Station</hi> (no nor one in a meaner) to ſay, that <hi>one ſingle Text of Scripture, does not contain all that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teacheth, touching an Article of Faith;</hi> or as the matter in hand is, a Complication of Doctrines out of Three or more Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of our Creed. Let Mr. <hi>P.</hi> inſinuate what he pleaſes of the Bp. no man of Senſe and Reaſon who conſiders this Text, and receives the <hi>Nicene Creed,</hi> and the <hi>Thirty Nine Articles</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> can ſay otherwiſe than the Bp. did. For let any Perſon read the Nicene Creed, and the Firſt of the Thirty Nine Articles, and ſay if <hi>All,</hi> that is in that Creed and Article touching this Miſtery, be <hi>expreſſed,</hi> or apparently <hi>implyed</hi> in <hi>that one Text.</hi> And finally as to the B—ps ſaying the Apoſtle ſpoke, <hi>what there he had occaſion to ſay, and what was to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,</hi> is moſt true. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> demands what that occaſion, what that purpoſe was? The Bp. anſwers out of <hi>ver.</hi> 1. and 5. It was <hi>to prove that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of GOD,</hi> (this the Apoſtle proves <hi>by three Witneſſes on Earth,</hi> and <hi>three Witneſſes in Heaven,</hi> ver. 6. 7, 8.) and by that means, to <hi>ſettle the Faith and Hope of Chriſtian Souls in the LORD JESUS.</hi> This was his purpoſe, and not fully there to declare the Doctrine of the Trinity; which is no where done in any one Text of Scripture, but is to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of many.</p>
            <p>To cut ſhort in theſe inſtances, wherein Mr. <hi>P.</hi> thought it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to confeſs his Faith, by ſuppoſing people would be ſo charitable as to infer from what he expreſt, that which by no rules of reaſoning would follow, all the World as well as the Bp. have reaſon to require of Mr. <hi>P.</hi> and his Party, a <hi>more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit confeſſion of Faith,</hi> if they expect to be accounted Chriſtians: And that for other reaſons than the Bp. has given: Eſpecially, this for one, That a great Perſon amongſt them, who profeſſes <hi>as concerning their Principles he was deceived by them, thinking</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:106565:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>they had held ſincerely the Principles, which by a more diligent ſearch, he finds they hold not,</hi> aſſures us, and has Printed Teſtimonies out of their Books to prove, they deny, 1. <q>Faith in Chriſt, as <note place="margin">
                     <hi>George Keith</hi> in his Third Narrative.</note> he outwardly ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as he roſe again, Aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and now Sits at the Right Hand of God, to be neceſſary to Salvation. 2. Juſtification by the Blood of Chriſt outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhed. 3. A Reſurrection of the Body that Dyeth. 4. Chriſts coming again, without us, in his glorified Body, to Judge the Quick and the Dead.</q> Nay the ſame Perſon profeſſes, as the Bp. has ſeen under his hand <q>That he really thinks he can prove <hi>W. P.</hi> holds not one of the Articles of the Chriſtian Creed, ſoundly and intirely, and that none ever more plainly oppug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Doctrine of the Scriptures than <hi>W. P.</hi> and his Party.</q> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo cloſe an Evidence as this is, let the World judge, if the Bp. be unreaſonable in demanding a better confeſſion of Faith, than by meer <hi>Innuendo's,</hi> as neceſſary to their being allowed Chriſtians. True indeed, now in his Defence Mr. <hi>P.</hi> tells the World he and his Brethren <hi>receive all the Articles of the Creed, called the Apoſtles,</hi> p. 97. But this may be reckoned one of the good effects, the Bps Paper has had, to bring them to this acknowledgment; and tis to be hoped they will be kept to it.</p>
            <p>It would be as endleſs as needleſs, and (beſides) would ſwell this Paper to too great a Bulk, to follow Mr. <hi>P.</hi> Page by Page, to the End, Replying to all his little Cavils and poor Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. A more Compendious way therefore muſt be taken. Which ſhall be 1. By reducing Mr. <hi>P—s</hi> Anſwers and Arguments to ſome Common Heads, or Figures of Speech, which he uſes; ſo contemptible in themſelves, as that the inſtances of them are anſwered by being ſhewn. And 2. by ſingling out the more material Points, wherein Mr. <hi>P.</hi> Enlarges, and ſetting them in their true Light.</p>
            <p>The ſeveral Heads to which his Anſwers may be reduced, are either <hi>manifeſt Impieties,</hi> or <hi>manifold arts of Uncharitableneſs</hi> and Diſingenuity, much unbecoming a Chriſtian, or even a fair Diſputant.</p>
            <p>Manifeſt Impieties are (1.) His falſifying the ſenſe of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and then the words of it ſo plainly, that he cannot well ſeem
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106565:6"/> inſenſible of it himſelf. Thus, whereas our LORD ſaid <hi>John</hi> III. 20. <hi>Every one that doeth evil hateth the light, neither cometh to the light, leſt his deeds ſhould be reproved.</hi> (Which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to make look favourably to his purpoſe,) he corrupts the <hi>21ſt verſe</hi> and reads it thus, <hi>He that loves the Light brings his Deeds to the Light, to ſee if they are wrought in GOD.</hi> p. 10. 4. Whereas the plain meaning of the Text is no more than, <hi>They that do evil ſeek to be hid.</hi> (1 Theſ. 5. 7. <hi>They that are Drunken, are Drunken in the Night.)</hi> They who do well fear not to be ſeen. To which ſenſe every Nation has Proverbs, <hi>Si factum eſt bonum quorſum tenebris opus eſt?</hi> and with us <hi>Truth ſeeks not Corners,</hi> with many like; now contrary to the ſenſe of Mankind, as well of the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>W. P.</hi> produces this Text as a proof of the Light within, and that it is to be <hi>the Rule and Judge of our Life and Deeds,</hi> yea <hi>to credit, confirm and expound Scripture.</hi> So does he too with like reaſonableneſs <hi>Eph.</hi> V. 11, 12, 13. (2.) His plain reproaching the Holy Spirit in the Apoſtles, as to what they taught. Thus when he had no other way to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Bps Argument, for the Divine Authority of Baptiſm by Water, taken from <hi>Acts X.</hi> 47. 48. he ſays plainly. <hi>In all which</hi> Peter <hi>ſeems more concerned to ſave his own credit, than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend or eſtabliſh Water-Baptiſm.</hi> p. 81. A man would think this were not expreſſing himſelf <hi>reverently on this tender point,</hi> or as he promiſed. p. 68. Theſe for a Taſt. Single inſtances under each Head, for brevity ſake muſt ſuffice.</p>
            <p>Manifold Arts of Uncharitableneſs and Diſingenuity, the Bp. accounts theſe that follow.</p>
            <p>1. Calumnious and Spiteful Inſinuations, as p. 30. that he, the Bp. <hi>believes not the Thirty Nine Articles,</hi> [yet did <hi>W. P.</hi> never diſcourſe with him, touching any one of them] with many like paſſages. 2. Falſe Imputations, p. 69. He downright charges the Bp. for treating the Quakers with Levity and Scorn, as to the Language <hi>Thou</hi> and <hi>Thee.</hi> The Bp. Challenges him, to ſhew a light or ſcornful Expreſſion in that his Paper. Nay rather than fail <hi>W. P.</hi> will impute to the Bp. his own uncharitable cenſures of him. The Biſhop according to his uſual way of plain dealing, and ſpeaking home to mens Conſciences, to the end they may ſearch
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106565:6"/> their Hearts, touching their ſecret and unſeen ſins, which are known only to God, and their own Conſciences, dealt roundly with the Quakers, and put ſome Queſtions to them, conjuring them to put them to themſelves, and Examine their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. For inſtance, the Bp. has long obſerved, and all Men may obſerve as Notorious, the Quakers eager purſuit of wealth, and their effectual, wily and ſecret ways of getting it. Now hereupon he bids them Examine their Conſciences, <q>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their main end and ſtudy by their pretended Mortifications and renouncing the World be not to enrich themſelves, and to make themſelves a party conſiderable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> This Mr. <hi>P.</hi> makes one of the Bps. cenſures, and then charges it upon the Bp. as <hi>the worſt conſtruction that the moſt irreligious and profane could make of their behaviour.</hi> The Bp. did not affix it to them and all along avows, that he ſuſpends any Cenſure or Judgment of them. He profeſſes, it is not his right in this ſenſe to judge. But he now demands of Mr. <hi>P.</hi> whether when Peoples Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are ſuſpicious, it be not reaſonable for, nay the Duty of, a faithful Paſtor, to conjure them to examine and judge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which is all the Bp. did. Yet ſtill Mr. <hi>P.</hi> goes on in this falſe imputation p. 117. <hi>The Bp.</hi> (ſays he,) <hi>tells us he will not judg us, yet his whole Paper is one continued Judgment of us.</hi> Sure Mr. <hi>P.</hi> does not know, or will not attend, what judging, as it means cenſoriouſneſs, is. The Bp. moſt plainly judged not the Quakers <hi>Belief in their Conſciences,</hi> but that Form, which Mr. <hi>P.</hi> and his Brethren <hi>profeſſed,</hi> or (to uſe their own term) <hi>decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> in this Paper. And the Bp. ſtands to it, both the <hi>Authors</hi> and the <hi>Paper deſerve</hi> another kind of <hi>Cenſure,</hi> then he gave, or attempted on Either. Notwithſtanding Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſticks not upon this very reaſon to charge the Bp. of <hi>Irreligion, making them as bad as bad can be,</hi> &amp;c. p. 117. God give Mr. <hi>P.</hi> more Charity and Reaſon; for this is plain cenſoriouſneſs, and concluding without conſequence. (3) Sly Jeers, p. 27. <hi>I would have my Reader reflect on this, though he were as big as a Bp.</hi> p. 40. [No Bp. in theſe three Kingdoms has the big and ſcornful look or deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Mr. <hi>P.</hi> eſpecially when he is in the humour of it.] <hi>The Bps. Hell—he keeps the true Hell to himſelf.</hi> [God deliver
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106565:7"/> Mr. <hi>P.</hi> from it.] But let him anſwer, how the Bp. could more clearly have Expreſt <hi>Hell,</hi> then by <hi>Eternity of Torments,</hi> the Term there uſed by the Bp. and declined by Mr. <hi>P.</hi> and his Brethren.</p>
            <p>4. Wilfully falſe Conſtructions of, and overlooking the Bps. ſenſe: Tergiverſations, ſhifting, pittiful Evaſions, &amp;c. For inſtance; <q>The Bp. had ſaid, they do not in their Paper own the Son of God to be ſo much as JESUS the (great Saviour, who delivereth from the wrath to come,) or the CHRIST (the great Prophet, Prieſt, Lord and King of the Church.)</q> Mr. <hi>P.</hi> anſwers, <hi>they ſeveral times call him CHRIST, admires at the Bps. palpable miſtake;</hi> Does <hi>W. P.</hi> then know no difference betwixt CHRIST and the CHRIST? betwixt calling a Perſon by his Name, and acknowledging his Authority, Office and Benefits? Again, the Bp. requires them to Embrace and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the intire Chriſtian Faith, in the points wherein he has ſhewn them defective, that is, as he proved in above two thirds of the Creed. <hi>W. P.</hi> anſwers, <hi>It would have become the Bp. to have told them, what he would have them believe,</hi> p. 38. Could the Bp. have ſpoke plainer, then he does, when he names the Articles of the Creed: which Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſay's he holds, therefore knows.</p>
            <p>5. Inconſequent and trifling Inferences ſuch are p. 31. <hi>We call him the beloved Son of God, the only begotten of the Father—</hi>Therefore <hi>conceived of the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> Mr. <hi>P.</hi> knows, <hi>Solomon</hi> was named JEDIDIAH, [the Lords beloved.] <hi>David</hi> ſaid to be <hi>his begotten Son,</hi> Pſ. 2. <hi>His firſt born.</hi> Pſ. 89. 27. Yet neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the Holy Ghoſt, nor born of a Virgin. Again in the ſame page, <hi>He that confeſſes him, made Fleſh, confeſſes him made Fleſh by God, and therefore made holy Fleſh:</hi> Does not all the World know, that all Fleſh is made by God, and do we hence conclude all Fleſh is Holy, or conceived by the Holy Ghoſt. Many more may be inſtanced.</p>
            <p>6. Contemptuous and ſcornful language: Such is that refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion, p. 61. <hi>A Weak-head,</hi> But let Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſcorn the Bp. as much as he pleaſes, he muſt know that for Men to Affect non-ſenſical language, and pretend Conſcience therein, and make it a mark
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106565:7"/> of Godlineſs and Holyneſs above others, (the thing taxed by the weak Bp.) is, when conſidered, <hi>a wicked kind of weakneſs,</hi> or voluntary making fools of Mens ſelves; together with <hi>an abuſe of Religion</hi> not to be endured: it was therefore no weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the Bp. to tax it, but a groſs one, and more then weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in <hi>W. P.</hi> to defend it.</p>
            <p>To theſe may be added his Cenſures all along, ſavouring of nothing, but the heighth of ſpiritual Pride and Uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. As, <hi>the Bp feels no ſhare in Chriſt, the glorious Light of Men,</hi> p. 47. He <hi>wants Acquaintance with the Spirit of God in his worſhip,</hi> &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe and the like Mr. <hi>P.</hi> muſt account for one day. God alone can judge in this caſe.</p>
            <p>To trouble a Mans ſelf, to wipe off ſuch dirt as this, would be almoſt as mean an Employment, as to caſt it. 'Twill fall off of its own accord. To wave therefore all theſe and many other Heads of Mr. <hi>Ps</hi> unhandſome dealing, which are only a diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to his cauſe and himſelf, (to his cauſe that needs ſuch a defence, and himſelf that could find no better,) the main part; in his whole Defence, that threaten doing hurt are; what he has of the <hi>Light</hi> within, of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and of that <hi>great point of Difference</hi> betwixt the Quakers and the Eſtabliſh'd Church.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt of theſe; the Bp. did ſay and ſtill ſtands to it, <hi>he knows not what to make of the Quakers Light within;</hi> But as to the <hi>true Divine Light,</hi> or the <hi>Holy Ghoſt convincing People, by the Holy Scripture, applied to Conſcience, of Sin, of Righteouſneſs, and of Judgment to come,</hi> the Bp. acknowledges it, and bleſſeth God for his ſhare thereof. Notwithſtanding he cannot yet perceive the Quakers, or Mr. <hi>P.</hi> himſelf know what they mean by Their Light. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> is a Man that had <hi>Academic Education,</hi> as he himſelf told the Bp.: and he often pretends to <hi>Logic</hi> and the Art of Diſputing? Now from ſuch a Perſon, when the <hi>meaning of a Term was</hi> demanded, ſome <hi>regular definition or explication of it,</hi> might have been expected; The Bp. had made four the moſt rational Conſtructions and Conjectures he could deviſe, of what they ſhould mean thereby. And diſtinctly propounded theſe, to have drawn out from Mr. <hi>P.</hi> a diſtincter and more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitive
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106565:8"/> ſenſe: In ſtead thereof Mr. <hi>P.</hi> rejects all with ſcorn and vile inſinuations, and only heaps up phraſes, and words darker and of more difficulty and uncertainty than the Term it ſelf: For their farther meaning referring to <hi>Barclay</hi>'s Book. The Bp. muſt tell Mr. <hi>P.</hi> that <hi>his Brother Barclay</hi> is guilty of the very ſelf-ſame <hi>unintelligible Banter,</hi> or (if that Term pleaſes not) Cant, on this head with himſelf; and no rational Man alive, can make ſenſe of what he has writ thereon; it being more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictious and inconſiſtent than Mr. <hi>Ps</hi> account. He in his V. Propoſition, which is touching this Light, firſt, plainly perverts the Holy Scripture, adding expreſly a new Term thereto, that he may prove Chriſt given as a Light to all: For he reads John III. 16. thus. <hi>God ſo loved the World, that he hath given his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Son a LIGHT, that whoſoever believeth in him ſhould be ſaved.</hi> As if either the Word <hi>a Light</hi> were in the Text, or Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Light only, would have ſaved Men, without his ſuffering for ſin; to which that Verſe particularly refers, as its imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate connexion with Verſ. 14, 15. ſhews. Then he miſapplies two or three other Texts, to prove this Light Univerſal. And in his Diſcourſe on this Propoſition §. 16. thus deſcribes it. <q>We underſtand not, ſaith he, his ſeed, Light or Grace to be an Accident, as moſt Men ignorantly do, but a real Spiritual Subſtance, which the Soul of Man is capable to feel and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, from which that real ſpiritual inward birth in Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ariſes, called the new Creature, the new Man in the Heart.</q> Yet this he tells us in his V. Propoſition above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, is <hi>the Purchaſe of Chriſts death for every Man, Lightening the Hearts of all in a day:</hi> And he adds in his VI. <hi>that the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt's Death and Sufferings as declared in Scripture, is not abſolutely neceſſary for making People partakers of this Light,</hi> and that <hi>they have erred who have taught it is.</hi> He goes on and proves it after his way, (§. 14.) to be <hi>a Subſtance not an Accident, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſubſiſts,</hi> [the Bp. by the way does not think this to be Scripture-Language, ſuch wherein, as Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſays, they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways teach, it ſubſiſts he ſays] <hi>in the Hearts of wicked Men, even whilſt they are in their wickedneſs.</hi> Then, of their <hi>feeling it,</hi> yea anon <hi>taſting, ſmelling, ſeeing it, handling by vertue of it the things</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:106565:8"/> 
               <hi>of God</hi> [which yet are certainly all ſpiritual things] and of their <hi>certain Experience thereof,</hi> and that they <hi>are able to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be true,</hi> he talks much. Now that our Lord Jeſus ſhould by his death have purchaſed for all Men and Women a new Spiritual Subſtance, which ſubſiſts in all even in wicked Men, and in a certain day inlightens them all, ſo as they may be ſaved, and that even without the knowledge of the Goſpel, that People ſhould be able to ſmell, and feel, and handle things which being intellectual and immaterial, can no wiſe be incident to theſe ſenſes, nor are ever ſo much as Metaphorically ſaid to be ſmelt, or handled, the Bp. does aver unintelligible, that is Banter. And ſuch is alſo his further Explication of it, §. 13, 14. p. 94, 95. too long to tranſcribe. And as for their reply which muſt be expected, that <hi>the Bp. is a carnally minded Man, to whom all this ſeems ſtrange,</hi> it ſhall be anſwered anon. In the mean while it muſt be demanded of Mr. <hi>P.</hi> what is become of his double record? <hi>The knowledge of the Scripture though com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and profitable is not needful,</hi> ſaith his Brother <hi>B.</hi> to whom he refers the Bp. for better underſtanding their Light: Which Light though both of them ſay, they feel and can make it appear to be true, the Bp. profeſſes ſincerely, he can not from any thing they have made appear, apprehend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible. But by what has been produced out of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clay</hi> in his own Words it appears Mr. <hi>Ps</hi> double and agreeing Teſtimony of the Light within, and the Scriptures of truth without, is but a new bubble upon the World: A thin leaf of Gold, to make the Poyſonous Pill of their Light within go down with leſs reluctancy or even ſuſpicion.</p>
            <p>Yet when he has thus gloſs'd the matter, he ſticks not to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>all the beſt and firſt Reformers</hi> Zwinglius, Luther, Melanch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thon, Calvin, Beza, Bucer, Peter Martyr <hi>and</hi> Eraſmus <hi>too, alſo our Excellent Martyrs,</hi> viz. Lambert, Rogers, Philpot, Bradford, Hooper, Woodman, &amp;c. <hi>to concur in this Aſſertion and Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;</hi> much at the ſame rate that he cites <hi>Clemens Romanus, Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullianus, Gregory Nazianzen, Clemens Alexandrinus, Auguſtin, Gregory the Great,</hi> &amp;c. And within a few lines more <hi>Petrus Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonius, Gratian, Cardan, Luther,</hi> without producing one Word
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106565:9"/> out of them, or referring to any treatiſe or page. After all which Pomp Mr. <hi>P.</hi> muſt not take it ill, if he be told, he cites Authors like a Man that never read them, or rather like one that never ſaw them. <hi>Zwinglius</hi> who has writ the leaſt of the Foreigners of the firſt Claſs he mentions, has three thick Folio's, oftner are they bound in four. <hi>Luther,</hi> beſides the Collection of his Works printed at <hi>Wittenberge,</hi> in 7 Folio's, has one more of <hi>Poſtills;</hi> and his <hi>Colloquia Menſalia,</hi> make up another, and there are other leſſer peices not contained in any of theſe. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> in the Old Edition, eleven Folio's, beſides diverſe French Works, never tranſlated into Latin; Now to add no more. Being that no Anſwer can be returned to an Argument from a Teſtimony, till the Teſtimony be produced, which ought to be in expreſs Terms, all this Allegation ought to paſs for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. But becauſe he and his followers may not go on in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting too much, the Bp. fairly avers, and takes upon him to prove, if Mr. <hi>P.</hi> or his Abetters ſhall deny it, that the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal of theſe Authors, we will take the four firſt, (which as to time ſhould have been ranged in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Order, <hi>Luther, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon, Zwinglius</hi> and <hi>Calvin,)</hi> as well as all other the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, or reformed, generally hold, (amongſt other points) theſe three that are expreſly contrary to what the Quakers teach of their Light within. They maintain (1) The Neceſſity of Revelation, or that the Knowledge of God by Scripture is neceſſary to Salvation in an ordinary way. This is expreſly contrary to a Light within, the purchaſe of Chriſts death for every Man, enlightning all in a day, even without the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Scripture. (2) The Divine Authority of the Holy Scriptures, and that all Illuminations of the Spirit, or pretended motions thereof are to be tryed by the written Word. This is contrary to making an Imaginary Light within the Rule of Mens Actions, and that even without (or ſometimes, as it comes to paſs in their <hi>Vagaries,</hi> againſt) Holy Scripture. (3) The Scriptures being its own Expoſitor; or that particular Texts are to be interpreted by others, or by the Analogy of Faith, and not by a private pretended Light of Mens own. If they ſhall ſay, the Bp. wrongs them, in ſaying, they make
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106565:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> their Light within <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Rule of their Actions at any time, without or againſt Holy Scripture, beſides what may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced out of their Books by way of Doctrine, (and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly out of <hi>W. P.</hi> p. 105.) Let them anſwer amongſt others, to theſe two matters of Fact, known all over the County of <hi>Cork.</hi> One <hi>Knight</hi> on a certain Lords-Day, in the time of Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ſtripping himſelf and leaving his Cloaths with his Brother in the Church-Yard, came wrapt in his Cloak, into the middle of the Congregation, and placing himſelf before the Miniſter, then in the Pulpit, after ſome time threw off his Cloak, and ſtood there ſtark naked (not ſo much as covering his <hi>Pudenda)</hi> but crying out <hi>Behold here the naked truth.</hi> Again<hi>—Workman</hi> in the Town of <hi>Roſs</hi> in the ſame County, gave out for a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, he would Faſt <hi>(i. e.</hi> Eat nothing) for Forty Days; and having Faſted many of them, being examined, utterly denyed he had Eaten any thing, onely ſaid he had waſhed his Mouth with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: But though he gave off before the Forty Days were near at an end, yet it was diſcovered, that in a Rick of Beans near his Chamber, he had made a great Hole, and devoured a ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble quantity of them. If theſe Men acted <hi>by a ſtrong impulſe of mind,</hi> as the Firſt of them is reported to have ſaid he did, the Bp. demands of Mr. <hi>P. Whether every ſtrong impulſe of mind is to be followed, as being the Light within?</hi> If not, what Rule have we to try the Light within by? If it be ſaid Scripture; agreed: But can Mr. <hi>P.</hi> produce a double and agreeing Record for theſe, and the like Actions? If he cannot, let him no longer palliate matters; but inſtead of ſeeking excuſes, confeſs plainly the ground of his Brethrens miſcarriage, to be the dangerous prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple he and they have taken up, and let him profeſs he is now for reforming it; but let him and them do it thorowly and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually: For there is no project ſo wild that their pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Light within may not lead them into. The Bp. could with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this County have aſſigned more Frantick, yea immoral in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, the effects of this pretended Light, but for diverſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons he has forborn them. And this is all he now thinks need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to ſay, as to the Light within.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Ps</hi> Citing of Authors being now mentioned, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106565:10"/> ſhould be given of his repeated Cunning, as well as Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſs, in citing another particular Writer againſt the Bp. <hi>His Cunning</hi> (and Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ought to have remembred who lately Printed that amongſt his Maxims, <hi>Cunning Borders upon Knavery)</hi> in that he never produces his Authors Words: And <hi>his unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi> in repreſenting the ſenſe widely different, if not contrary to what it is. <hi>Ouzelius</hi> in his Notes on <hi>Minutius Foelix</hi> tells us, the Primitive Chriſtians forbore the Heatheniſh Cuſtoms, and particularly therefore they rejected the Cuſtom of Crowning their Dead with Garlands: This Mr. <hi>P.</hi> refers to (if he refer to any thing to be found in that Author) to Juſtifie the Quakers af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting Dreſſes, different from other Chriſtians of their degree: Is there no difference betwixt Idolatrous Rites, and the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Faſhions of Chriſtians ordinary Apparrel! But to return to <hi>Minutius,</hi> whereas <hi>Coecilius</hi> the Heathen had there objected to the Chriſtians, that as ſoon as they ſaw one another, they knew each other <hi>[Occultis notis &amp; inſignibus]</hi> by ſecret Marks and Signes; <hi>Octavius</hi> the Chriſtian Anſwers, they knew one another onely by <hi>their Innocence and Humility, not by any Bodily Mark.</hi> This the Bp. takes to be rather againſt the Quakers ſingularity in Dreſſes, Faſhions and Behaviour; And as to their Language af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all Artifices, Mr. <hi>P.</hi> has not been able to produce, (which was a preſſing point of his Buſineſs) one Precedent or Shadow of a Teſtimony, that the Primitive Chriſtians uſed not the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Civilities in their common Diſcourſe and Salutations; but affected a different Style or Way by themſelves. Contrarily he might have remembred, that the beloved Diſciple, being to Write to a Chriſtian Siſter of Quality, Salutes her by an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, <hi>To the Elect Lady.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Head worth taking notice is <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> Touching which the Bp. ſincerely profeſſes, he Mourns to ſee Men ſo hardned as it appears, by Mr. <hi>Ps.</hi> wreſting Scripture to elude the Truth, he is, in this matter: Mr. <hi>P.</hi> firſt in a manner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes himſelf put to his Shifts<hi>—I am ſenſible of the diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage I am under,</hi> &amp;c. ſaith he, p. 68. yet proceeds he to ſhift on; But to reduce all into as ſhort a compaſs as may be: The Bp. had avouched thoſe words of our LORD <hi>Matth.</hi> XXVIII. 19.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106565:10"/> to be an Inſtitution and Command of Baptiſm with Water: And gave two ſubſtantial reaſons, which he holds to. <q>1. Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing with the Holy Ghoſt (ſaid the Bp.) was not in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles power. Therefore it could not be the thing commanded them. 2. Baptiſing with Water was the Apoſtles and Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Practice, and has been ever ſince, the Practice of the Church.</q> To the Firſt of theſe Mr. <hi>P.</hi> anſwereth it is not true, and to make that good alledges <hi>Acts</hi> X. 44. <hi>While</hi> Peter <hi>yet ſpake theſe words, the Holy Ghoſt fell on all thoſe that heard the word:</hi> Hence he infers that <hi>Peter</hi> Baptiſed <hi>Cornelius</hi> with the Holy Ghoſt Now was there ever any thing more impertinent and inconſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent? <hi>While</hi> Peter <hi>ſpake,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the Holy Ghoſt fell on them,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore (which was the Point to be proved) was it <hi>Peter</hi>'s Act, and in his power to Baptiſe with the Holy Ghoſt: No; <hi>The Spirit breatheth where it liſteth</hi> John III. 8. But <hi>GOD,</hi> ſays Mr. <hi>P. by the Apoſtles did Baptiſe Believers with the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Did he ſo? Then 'twas GOD Baptiſed them with the Holy Ghoſt, and not the Apoſtles. They were only inſtruments at pleaſure; as long as the Act was not principally theirs, it cannot be concluded hence to have been in their power. <hi>Baptiſing with the Holy Ghoſt and with Fire</hi> (the words Mr. <hi>P.</hi> alledges p. 69. and runs upon) was a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Prerogative of our Lord Chriſt, predicted only of him <hi>Matth.</hi> IV. 11. and fulfilled only by him <hi>(Acts</hi> II.) not by any man ever living. The Bps. Firſt Reaſon then is true.</p>
            <p>But <hi>his Second</hi> (ſays Mr. <hi>P.) ſeems to be defective and ſhort,</hi> yet all the ſubſtance that Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſpeaks in 12 or 13 Pages to prove it ſo, is, <hi>Practice is no Inſtitution.</hi> Nor was the Bp. ſo weak as to pretend it is. But by Mr. <hi>Ps.</hi> leave, continued Practice in obedience to Command, and ſuch Practice allowed, urged and re-inforced by the Holy Ghoſt, is a good Explication of the ſenſe of the Inſtitution, or of the words of the Command. The ſumm of the Command was, <hi>Baptiſe them that Believe.</hi> The ſumm of the Practice purſuant is, <hi>All thoſe that believed were<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> the Apoſtles or Perſons Commiſſionated by them, <hi>Baptiſed with Water.</hi> Yea though they had been before Baptiſed with the Holy Ghoſt, as the Bp. pleaded from <hi>Acts</hi> X. 47. Was ever any Inſtitution more clearly evidenced and aſſerted? As to all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106565:11"/> Mr. <hi>Ps. agravating Excurſions</hi> on this Subject, he full well knows the Church of <hi>England-men,</hi> no more allow Water-Baptiſm to be ſufficient to the Salvation of adult perſons, without the New Creature, or Baptiſm of the Spirit, then he does. But ſome Perſons have the faculty to be blind when they liſt; to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict and accuſe, even againſt their own Senſe: Thus as to what Mr. <hi>P.</hi> has Replyed touching Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>As to the Lords-Supper, that ſtands upon the ſame unmove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Foundation with Baptiſm, <hi>viz.</hi> our LORD's Inſtitution, and the continued Univerſal Practice of the Church. To what the Bp. had mentioned of the firſt of theſe Mr. <hi>P.</hi> excepts in theſe words. <q>The Bp. will have this Supper Four times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated in the Scripture of the New Teſtament, beſides that of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> which muſt be his miſtake.</q> Whereto the Bp. ſays, To report his words thus, is not Mr. <hi>Ps.</hi> miſtake, but in all appearance his wilful prevarication. The Bp. ſaid, <hi>no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand could be more expreſs then that touching the Outward uſe of Bread and Wine in the Lords Supper, Four times repeated,</hi> [namely the Command] <hi>in the New Teſtament;</hi> and that <hi>St.</hi> Paul <hi>adds</hi> (as a reaſon of the Command, and Argument for its Obſervation) <hi>it is a ſhewing forth the LORD's Death till he came.</hi> All this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing undeniable, Mr. <hi>P.</hi> that he might have ſomething to except againſt, was forced to miſreport the Bps. words. Is there not a vaſt difference betwixt rheſe two Aſſertions, <hi>This Supper was Four times repeated,</hi> and the <hi>Command for this Supper is Four times repeated, or recorded in the New Teſtament?</hi> Which laſt was moſt evidently the Bps. ſenſe.</p>
            <p>But, having to his Credulous Readers (that is his own Party) convinced in his way (that is charged) the Bp. of a miſtake, he proceeds (to what is more dangerous) plainly to diffuſe his Poiſon. <q>This coming of CHRIST was Spiritual—and the words may reaſonably be Read [he means Paraphraſed] thus, <hi>Eat this Supper of outward Bread and Wine, till I come and Sup with you, and be your Supper, that am the Bread and Wine from Heaven,</hi> &amp;c.</q> [By Mr. <hi>Ps.</hi> favour the Scripture no where ſtyleth CHRIST <hi>Wine from Heaven.</hi> In reſpect of the Union of the Saints with him he is ſtyled a <hi>Vine;</hi> and his Grace
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106565:11"/> or Spirit in reſpect of its indeficiency <hi>Water,</hi> and <hi>Living Water,</hi> but no where Wine. This a fetch of Mr. <hi>Ps.</hi> who (as his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) uſes to make Scripture for us, as well as wreſt it.] But as to the Interpretation by him advanced. Though here be a Doubt or Ambiguity raiſed, where there is none, yet ſuppoſe (not admit) the Text doubtful: However, let that be the ſenſe of it, which the Saints in Scripture, ever underſtood to be ſuch. If then they, in whom CHRIST JESUS was already come, and in whom he dwelt continually, even by the power of his Spirit, did notwithſtanding this, ſome of them dayly, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers every Lords-Day, celebrate this his Supper, Then this ſhewing forth his Death <hi>till he came,</hi> was not by them under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of his <hi>Inward</hi> and <hi>Spiritual,</hi> but of his <hi>Second Outward</hi> coming to Judgement. For in ſuch Caſe, feeling ſo fully his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come in their Hearts, they would have deſiſted. But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their having received the Holy Ghoſt, and CHRIST's dwelling in them by his Spirit, they in ſome places, and while the Diſciples dwelt together in Common, dayly Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated the Lords Supper <hi>(Acts</hi> II. 46.) and in others, where they were diſperſed amongſt the Heathens, they met on the Firſt Day of the Week to Celebrate it: <hi>(Acts</hi> XX. 7.) There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Saints in Scripture, had no ſuch Notion of our LORD's coming in this caſe, nor did they underſtand it as Mr. <hi>P.</hi> has wreſted it of an inward, but of an outward coming, as the Church Univerſally has ever taken it ſince that day, to this preſent.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>P.</hi> has another touch, which may ſtumble ſome, for lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide Baptiſm and the Lords Supper. <q>Theſe viſible Signs (ſaith he) which the Bp. calls the Badges of Chriſtianiiy, are not made an Article of any of the antient Creeds.—Had they been of that importance, they are by ſome eſteemed, we cannot think they would have been forgot, by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilers of thoſe Creeds.</q> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Nor were they forgot. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was never Catechiſed, as he ought to have been, or has forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten what he was taught, to be the meaning of that Article. <hi>I believe the Holy Catholick Church, the Communion of Saints.</hi> That is in ſhort, I believe all the Faithful are made one Body by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in the ſame Faith, Covenant and Ordinances of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106565:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> eſpecially Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper. But in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinopolitan Creed which was Compiled about the Year 379 or 380, when Re-baptiſing of Hereticks had been for ſome time matter of Controverſie, and had turmoil'd the Church, it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, <hi>I believe one Catholick Church; I acknowledge one Baptiſm for the Remiſſion of Sins.</hi> That is, Perſons being once Baptiſed, and thereby ingrafted into the Church, ought not to be Baptiſed again; which is the true ſenſe of one Baptiſm, and not what Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſuggeſts. Further, were Mr. <hi>P.</hi> ſuch a thorough read Man as he would ſeem, the Creeds of the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> to whom he would have us (as he pretends) more conformable, might have ſatisfied him in this point. In one of which, preſented by them to <hi>Uladiſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Hungary</hi> (extant <hi>in Faſcic: Rerum expet: &amp; fugiend.</hi> p. 162.) there are two diſtinct Articles, one of Baptiſm, the other of the Euchariſt, too large to be here inſerted. And in another more brief which is to be ſeen in <hi>Hovedens Annalls,</hi> fol. 319. we have theſe words. <q>We believe that no man is ſaved who Eats not the Body of CHRIST, which Body is not Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated but in the Church, and by a Prieſt. We believe alſo that none is ſaved unleſs he be Baptiſed, and that Infants are ſaved by Baptiſm.</q> This Creed is alſo produced by Arch-Biſhop <hi>Uſher,</hi> in his learned Book <hi>De ſucceſs: &amp; ſtat. Chriſt. Eccl. cap.</hi> 8. To mention the Creeds of other Churches, would ſignifie little in Mr. <hi>Ps.</hi> opinion: and the Bp. knows not how much Authority, he will allow the poor <hi>Waldenſes</hi> now, when he finds they are againſt him; but let him take it as he pleaſes, he muſt know the conſent of all Chriſtians, from the time of the firſt Inſtitution of the Lord's-Supper, as has been ſhewn, runs againſt this his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the Text. To ſumm up all in brief that has been now ſaid, of the Sacraments. The Bp. ſays to Renounce or caſt off the outward Badges of the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity, which our LORD CHRIST Inſtituted, and his Apoſtles deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and which the Apoſtolical Churches received, and conſtantly practiced, which all Chriſtian Churches ever ſince have held to, is to renounce or caſt off the outward Profeſſion of Chriſtianity. Put M. <hi>P.</hi> and his Party renounce or caſt off theſe outward Badges of the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity, which Chriſt Jeſus appointed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106565:12"/> and his Apoſtles delivered, which the Apoſtolical Churches re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and conſtantly practiced, which all Chriſtian Churches ever ſince have held to. Therefore Mr. <hi>P.</hi> and his Party have recounced or caſt off, the outward profeſſion of Chriſtianity, that is, outwardly are no Chriſtians. As to their Hearts, the Bp. leaves them to GOD, and Judges not. And thus as to the Sacraments.</p>
            <p>The laſt Point, which the Bp. thinks of moment in Mr. <hi>Ps.</hi> Book yet remaining untoucht, is <hi>The great difference or Ground of Diſſent betwixt the Quakers and the Eſtabliſht Church,</hi> and this Mr. <hi>P.</hi> tells us is the <hi>great Carnality and Emptineſs both of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and People, under the profeſſion of Religion amongſt us—A humane and lifeleſs Miniſtry and Worſhip, together with the great Worldlineſs of Profeſſors—The Miniſtry being made a Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Preferment—Turning Alms into Dues, and by Law mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gifts Rents.</hi> p. 97, 98, 99. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) As to Carnality Mr. <hi>P.</hi> muſt not be offended, if he having exempted himſelf and Party from all this Guilt, and charged it upon the Eſtabliſht Church and Miniſtry, the Bp. hereby enforced ſpeak out. He ſays then that if Eating the Fat, and Drinking the choiceſt, be Carnality, if minding world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Gain, and being ſo intent on it Day and Night, as to paſs moſt Days in the Week without a Prayer to GOD, either in publick Aſſembly or Family, if the ſlyeſt ways both to get Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and keep it be worldlineſs, he knows no ſort of People, according to the degree of each, more given to theſe Vices than the Quakers. There is nothing to be Eaten which is better than Ordinary, that comes into our Markets here, which the People obſerve not preſently bought up by the Quakers. They are ſtill the earlieſt and beſt Chapmen every Market-Day, for ſuch Commodities, and much good may they do them. The Bp. could mention more ſcandalous Particulars or Inſtances, both of Carnality and Worldlineſs amongſt them, but it is not agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his Temper. And indeed how they ſhould be a <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly minded</hi> People who ſo much reſtrain <hi>Prayer, that is, lay a ſide, forbear or neglect it, as to common Practice</hi> (at leaſt have done ſo till of very late Years, and defended the ſame, as the Bp.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106565:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> could ſpeak upon his own knowledge) is not accountable. Next, as to the point of their <hi>being Spiritual,</hi> becauſe we of the Eſtabliſht Church are often taxed of want hereof, and ſo charged of being unable to underſtand the Works of the Holy Ghoſt, which they feel, Mr. <hi>P.</hi> muſt give the Bp. leave to be a little more particular alſo on this Term.</p>
            <p>Let Mr. <hi>P.</hi> then know, that whatever mens <hi>attainments</hi> may be, it is not good to <hi>boaſt</hi> ſo much of their being <hi>Spiritual;</hi> and <hi>greater boaſting</hi> certainly there cannot be, than for men to <hi>claim Spiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> to themſelves <hi>alone,</hi> and pronounce all the reſt of the Chriſtian World Carnal. To ſpeak to the true Notion of Spirituality: ſuch Spiritual Perſons, as Mr. <hi>P.</hi> pretends to be, and as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> XI. (the place ſo much inſiſted on by Mr. <hi>P.</hi> p. 53, And ever and anon alluded to, by him and his followers) neither Mr. <hi>P.</hi> is, nor any Perſon that we know, now living. Namely they can none of them <hi>Preach in demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Spirit and Power.</hi> verſ. 4. They have not thoſe extraordinary gifts of the Spirit, as that they are able to <hi>ſpeak with Tongues, and Propheſy,</hi> or to <hi>Heal</hi> the Diſeaſed by word or touch, or to tell us the ſecrets of mens Hearts. Which Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous powers were the demonſtration of the Spirit their intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. They cannot by ſuch works convince the World, that they have Myſteries, and the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> (which has been hidden from the very Princes and Wiſe-men of the World) <hi>revealed to them by the Spirit</hi> of GOD, as thoſe Perſons had, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. The <hi>knowledge of CHRIST Crucified,</hi> and GOD's deſign of ſaving Mankind by him; of <hi>making him to us Wiſdom and Righteouſneſs, and Sanctification and Redemption,</hi> (1. <hi>Cor.</hi> I. 3. The Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries St. <hi>Paul</hi> delivered to the <hi>Corinthians)</hi> were not by our Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers attained by any other Revelation, than that of Scripture: nor could they ever have been attained unto, much leſs proved, by Mans Wiſdom or natural abilities and methods <hi>ver.</hi> 13, 14. But tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e things <hi>Paul</hi> and others then <hi>ſpiritually received</hi> (namely by Revelation of the Spirit as <hi>verſ.</hi> 10.) Now ſuch Spirituality as this, (Let Mr. <hi>P.</hi> pretend to what he will) is long ſince ceaſed, and it was foretold it ſhould ceaſe. <hi>Whether there be Propheſies they ſhall fail, whether there be Tongues they ſhall ceaſe, whether there be</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106565:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Knowledge</hi> (of ſuch inſpired kinds as above) <hi>it ſhall vaniſh away.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 8. Accordingly all theſe as to what was Immediate and Extraordinary, we ſee long ſince not to have been in the Church. And further, as to thoſe Heroick or Tranſcendent degrees of Holineſs, (or of all Chriſtian Virtue) ſo ſuddenly infuſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many Primitive Saints, and accompanying the aforeſaid Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Gifts, at the firſt great effuſion of the Spirit, whereby men were after a ſort created Saints, of the firſt Magnitude, the Bp. is well aſſured, that the experience of Mankind has long am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply convinced the World, this kind of Spiritual men are ceaſed. People are now made holy by the uſe of outward means, and grow up in Grace by degrees. Yet in both caſes, as to Gifts as well as Holineſs, there are thoſe who, by Analogy and Proportion, may be ſtill termed Spiritual; that is, there are Perſons who by Study and Induſtry, attain to ſpeak with Tongues, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Others who having from the Holy Scriptures, which were Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Spirit of GOD, learnt <hi>the mind of the Spirit,</hi> and been in their Hearts perſwaded of the Truths and Duties they have thence learnt, and felt their Souls ſtrongly moved, by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Spirit, under the Miniſtry of the word, to the Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of ſuch Duties, have yielded themſelves, and ſubmitted to the Conduct of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>leading them</hi> by Scripture <hi>into all Truth,</hi> as well as Holineſs. They allow themſelves in no known Sin, nor in the neglect of any known Duty; If they are overtaken through human frailty by any Evil, they immediatly repent and return, with new Zeal, to their Duty, <hi>purging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> [to their power] <hi>from all Filthineſs, both of Fleſh and Spirit.</hi> Now having their Hearts habituated to ſuch new Life, which by the power of the Spirit they have been brought over to, theſe Perſons may juſtly be called in their degree Spiritual. And having their Paſſions mortified, their Senſe and Belief of true good changed, their Counſels and Wills by ſuch belief guided and governed, they do certainly judge at another rate in all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Practice, than they themſelves did, or the vain, giddy, worldly, wicked part of Mankind do. They have their daily frequent retirements to Devotion, and (beſides) their Hearts even amidſt their common buſineſs much with GOD. Their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106565:14"/> thoughts and affections dwell much in Heaven, and they are ever and anon in their Souls, breathing and ſecretly gaſping af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Country. Now let ſuch Perſons as theſe be allowed to be Spiritual: and if ſo, the Bp. ſays, he doubts not but there will be found more ſuch who are no Quakers, than who really are. Particularly, the Bp. claims to be ſuch a one himſelf, and Challenges Mr. <hi>P.</hi> to prove the Contrary: And being in this ſenſe (which is all by any can be juſtly pretended to) a Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Man, he is able thus <hi>Spiritually to diſcern the things of GOD,</hi> to diſcourſe of them with feeling and favour, and he thanks GOD, he is no ſtranger to ſuch Light and Operations of the Holy Spirit, let Mr. <hi>P.</hi> cenſure of ſay what he pleaſes: In the mean while, the Bp. does not Monopoliſe Spirituality either to himſelf, or the Church he his of: But touching both, rather chooſes to take up the words of the Holy Apoſtle. 2. Cor. X. 12. <hi>We dare not make our ſelves of the number, or compare our ſelves with ſome that commend themſelves, but they meaſuring themſelves by themſelves, and comparing themſelves amongſt themſelves</hi> (perhaps) <hi>are not wiſe.</hi> And thus much as to the Quakers imputing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Carnality, to thoſe of the Eſtabliſht Church, and ingroſſing Spirituality to themſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) As to our Emptineſs, The Bp. craves pardon if he be at a loſs, what Mr. <hi>P.</hi> means hereby. If Emptineſs ſignifie the Miniſters Sermons being barren (with little Subſtance or ſolid Matter in them) the Quakers are much more guilty, as far as ever the Bps. Experience could reach: Witneſs the firſt things they Publiſhed, if compared to the Printed Sermons of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable Clergy. Since Mr. <hi>Ps.</hi> Acceſſion to them, it muſt be confeſt he has much improved them, and brought them to Write what looks like Senſe and Coherence: But the Bp. would willingly know of Mr. <hi>P.</hi> what there was in <hi>Betty Wheadons</hi> holding forth, who on a certain day ſpoke in their Meeting, after Mr. <hi>P. at Cork,</hi> and would be heard, when he put his Hat before his Face and Laughed? And whether She be the only Perſon, from whom in their Aſſemblies he has often heard ſuch Stuff. Let Mr. <hi>P.</hi> be ingenuous, and no more of this.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, That the <hi>Altars</hi> being made a proviſion for thoſe <hi>who with</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:106565:14"/> 
               <hi>wait on the Altar,</hi> ſhould alienate any Mens minds from Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeems as monſtrous, and unreaſonable injuſtice, as well can be imagined; and if there be any truth in that of the Apoſtle, (1. <hi>Cor.</hi> IX. 13, 14.) moſt contrary to GOD's Ordinance. It appears that grounds of offence are very ſcarce, when this is made one. Such things as theſe are ſaid, becauſe ſomething muſt be ſaid. A Man who conſiders this, will be ſtrangely tempted to an unluckky gueſs, whence that Perſon has taken in his Principles, who would have ſo great a body as the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry in theſe Kingdoms, all to become ſomewhat like Mendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant Friars. No Rents or Dues muſt be allowed them, but Alms and Gifts. What then? Are they likely to be more ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere in their Doctrine, by being put to pleaſe Men, that they may give them an Alms? Miraculous ſupports are ceaſed with Miracles themſelves. The Bp. does not aggravate the matter. Mr. <hi>P.</hi> no where moves that thoſe Laws made, repeated and continued for ſo many Ages, which forbid Miniſters to exerciſe Merchandiſe, Mechannicks, or ſecular Imployments, may be abrogated or taken away. If then being forbid otherways of getting a livelyhood, their Lands and Tythes muſt be denyed them, there remains nothing for them, but going a Begging; and would this mend the manners of the World, or make Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind more readily or more firmly believe Religion? If Mr. <hi>P.</hi> be not <hi>Popiſhly affected,</hi> which has been long feared of him, (and that on very likely grounds) it may be ſuſpected hence, that he has a greater kindneſs for Atheiſm, then is conſiſtent with his Profeſſion; in as much as he is ſo much Offended, that there is an order of men honourably maintained, whoſe buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it is to keep up ſober Religion, and the true old Chriſtian Faith in the Nation. The Bp. doubts not to affirm, that take away the Eſtabliſht Miniſtry (which in moral ſpeaking cannot ſubſiſt without a maintenance) and let our Pariſh Churches be left deſtitute of learned Preachers, not onely Popery in ſome places, but Irreligion and Barbarity more generally would ſoon enſue.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding, and in ſpite of all ſuch ill Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, if <hi>they who Preach the Goſpel do live upon the Goſpel</hi> (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> allowed they ſhould) in Mr. <hi>Ps.</hi> Judgment, they muſt be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106565:15"/> all <hi>Hirelings</hi> and <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> and <hi>the Bp. himſelf need not look far for ſuch—He is too ſenſibly inſtructed in this affair,</hi> ſays Mr. <hi>P.</hi> for a par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing Blow. Whereto all the Defence the Bp. makes, is to appeal from this Sentence, to the ſearcher of all Hearts, who knows, that as he inclined from a Child his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heart, to prepare for the ſerving him in the Miniſtry, and through great Difficulties brought him to that Office, ſo gave he to him a free and reſolved Soul, to go through all, what ever ſhould come, whether ill Report, or good Report, Poverty or Riches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nor does the Bp. doubt but Thouſands of his Brethren in the Miniſtry, can as honeſtly as himſelf appeal from Mr. <hi>Ps.</hi> uſurped judicature to that juſter Judge. The Bp. mean while, for himſelf, hereby ſummons's <hi>W. P.</hi> to appear before GOD ſhortly at his Tribunal, to anſwer for his Cenſuring him as mercenary, an Hireling and an Hypocrite, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bold to tell the World, that both he, and divers of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren with him, in a certain City laboured in the Miniſtry both Night and Day, when they had neither Lands nor Tyths, nor other Revenues to ſupport them: And that in the heighth of Dangers and depth of Spoils, they failed not to feed their Flock with Diligence, Conſtancy, and Courage: That the very Perſons, and others of their Party, who now call that <hi>ſpoiling</hi> which is but making ſome of their Party pay a ſmall pittance of <hi>legal Dues</hi> that they can well ſpare, were at that time in power at Court or otherwiſe, and inſtead of <hi>Preaching</hi> (which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend themſelves to be ſpecially called to) were <hi>directors of the publick Counſels;</hi> for no good, or much miſchief. Again, if that may prove the Bps. Chriſtian Spirit, he can ſay, maugre Mr. <hi>Ps.</hi> Inſinuations, he never Perſecuted Quaker, no nor any Vituous and quiet Diſſenter, when he had the moſt power. He has been in many caſes tender, not only of their Perſons, but even of their good Names; and particularly has hindred a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Perſon from publiſhing Memoirs of Mr. <hi>Ps.</hi> Life, of his turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Quaker, of his buſineſs at St. <hi>Omers, &amp;c.</hi> All theſe things and many others the Bp. could ſay for aſſerting his own and Brethrens Innocency and Sincerity, and thereby aggravate the Vile and undeſerved Treatment, Mr. <hi>P.</hi> has beſtowed upon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106565:15"/> him in his unhandſome Piece: But he checks his Pen; and inſtead of aggravations adds only this Prayer, That GOD will forgive all to Mr. <hi>P,</hi> and his Brethren; and beſtow upon them a Spirit of true Faith, Meekneſs and Peace; of Heavenly mindedneſs, Charity, Mortification, and all the Graces they pretend to; And that their Hearts may be one day found as void of Error, Pride, Scorn and Peeviſh Rancor, as Mr. <hi>Ps.</hi> Book is full of the Expreſſions of them all.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Cork</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 21. 1698/9.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 11. line 11. blot out <hi>of.</hi> p. 13. l. ult r. <hi>Cardan.</hi> p. 14. l. 19. blot out <hi>to.</hi> p. 15. l. 1. blot out <hi>the.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
